Guide to the Harris Masterson, Jr. Papers, 1894-1920, bulk 1898-1902 MS 469
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Harris Masterson, Jr. Papers
1894-1920
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Masterson, Harris, Jr.
MS 469
8 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
These papers cover Houston born chaplain and educator Harris Masterson, Jr.'s life from his schooling through his career with the YMCA. Highlights include correspondence with family members, photographs, school materials and his career.
Biographical Note
Harris Masterson, Jr., born June 22, 1881, Brazoria, TX, was the son of Judge Harris Masterson and Sallie Stewart Turner. A graduate of the University of the South in Sewanee, TN (1904) and the Episcopal Theological School of Cambridge [Harvard] (1907), Masterson began his career as chaplain of All Saint's, Austin, TX, 1908-11. He worked with the YMCA in China (Hankow and Wuchang, 1911-16) and the US (1916-17), and became a Red Cross chaplain in 1918. He came to Houston in 1919 to become the organizer, director and chaplain of a community house for Rice Institute students, later known as Autry House. Masterson was active in civic and educational affairs and served in various positions including chairman of the Building Committee of the Houston Public Library Board and as a Trustee for the University of the South. In 1925 he married Elizabeth Simpkins who shared his work with Rice students. The Mastersons moved to France to work with American students in Paris and returned to Austin, TX in 1926 for Masterson to become Rector of All Saint's Chapel. He resigned in Oct. 1935 and died in Austin in Nov. 1935.
Scope and Contents
The collection, totaling nine document boxes, covers Harris Masterson, Jr.'s life from his schooling through his career with the YMCA. Highlights include correspondence with family members, photographs, school materials and his career.
Access Restrictions
No access restrictions; this material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
The papers originally were part of the deposit of the Masterson Family Collection given by Harris Masterson, III (HMJr.'s nephew) in 1966. They were separated from the original deposit in May, 1998.
Related Material
Judge Harris Masterson Papers MS 468
Harris Masterson, III Papers MS 470
James Lockhart Autry Papers MS 003
Autry House; Carroll and Harris Masterson, III; Neill T. Masterson and Libbie J. Masterson information/vertical files, Woodson Research Center.
Index Terms
Subjects
Religion
Document Types
photographs; notes; postcards; corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Masterson family
Subjects (Corporations)
Autry House (Houston, Tex.); YMCA Army Educational Commission; Episcopal Church. Clergy. Correspondence; Young Men's Christian Associations of North America. International Committee; Young Men's Christian Associations of China
- Series I: Correspondence, 1898-1920; 23710 (Box 1-2)
  - Subseries A: General, 1898-1917; 23722 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - Houston Transfer and Carriage Company, 1907-14; 23729 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Houston Transfer and Carriage Company, 23728 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Esther H. Sharp to HMJr., 1900-03; 23727 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - J.P. Murdoch to HMJr., 1898-1902; 23726 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nora Macclean to HMJr., 1898-1900, n.d.; 23725 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Wm. Alexander Percy, 1900-04; 23724 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - HMJr. letters, misc., 1898-1917; 23723 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Family, 1898-1920; 23711 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
    - "Sis" [Roene Masterson Cage] to HMJr., 1898-1902; 23721 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chaille Margaret Jones [cousin?] to HMJr., 1900; 23720 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Annie Masterson [aunt] to HMJr., 1900; 23719 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Christiana Masterson [grandmother] to HMJr., 1898, n.d.; 23718 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mary Masterson [cousin] to HMJr., 1898-1900; 23717 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - LJM [step-mother] to HMJr., 1898-1903; 23716 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Elliott Cage [brother-in-law] to HMJr., 1899-1903; 23715 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Leigh C. Masterson [cousin] to HMJr., 1989-1903; 23714 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Neill T. Masterson [brother] to HMJr., 1898-1900, n.d.; 23713 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Harris Masterson [father] to HMJr., 1898-1920; 23712 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II: Personal, 1894-1920; 23695 (Box 3-4)
  - Diary, "My Thoughts", 1894-c. 1899; 23709 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Logic notebook, n.d.; 23708 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notes, 1902-04; 23707 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Parochial Register, or Rector's Private Record", c.1909; 23706 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - HMJr. published work, "An Adamite", 1912; 23705 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Essays, c. 1901-10; 23704 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - University of the South, Sewanee, TN, receipts/corresp., 1899-1904; 23703 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Episcopal Theological School at Harvard, 1904-06; 23702 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sermons, religious materials, 1900-1915; 23701 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Misc. vouchers, receipts, checks, 1900-20; 23700 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bank records, c. 1898-1921; 23699 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Masterson and related families genealogical materials, 23698 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Misc. materials, 23697 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Misc. correspondence envelopes, 23696 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series III: YMCA, 1908-1917; 23663 (Box 5-8)
  - Subseries A: China, International YMCA, 23673 (Box 5-6)
    - Sub-subseries 1. General, 23688 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
      - Reports, statements, financial, c. 1910-14; 23694 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Reports, statements, financial, c. 1911-15; 23693 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Sermons, notes, prayers, n.d.; 23692 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Published materials, newsclips, c. 1911-16; 23691 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Receipts, 1910-14; 23690 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Personal, c. 1912-14; 23689 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sub-subseries 2.: Correspondence, 23674 (Box 5-6)
      - General, 23687 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Fletcher S. Brockman to HMJr., 1912-15, n.d.; 23686 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Edward Fitzgerald to HMJr., 1906-08; 23685 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - A.S. Lloyd to HMJr., 1915-16, n.d.; 23684 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Hugh A. Moran to HMJr., 1911-14, n.d.; 23683 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - J.R. Mott to HMJr., 1913-15; 23682 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - L.H. Roots to HMJr., 1908-15, n.d.; 23681 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Archie T.L. Tsen to HMJr., 1914-15; 23680 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - James H. Wallace to HMJr., 1914, n.d.; 23679 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Ling Wei to HMJr., 1914-15, 1917, n.d.; 23678 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - H.A. Wilbur to HMJr., 1914-15; 23677 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Misc. correspondence envelopes, 23676 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Pamphlets/booklets/flyers related to China YMCA and missionary work, 23675 (Box 6)
  - Subseries B: ARMY YMCA, 23664 (Box 7-8)
    - Administration, c. 1916-17; 23672 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1915-17; 23671 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Course work/lectures, 23670 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Financial, 1917; 23669 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Newsclips, publications, 23668 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Rosters, subscriptions, 1916-17; 23667 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Misc., 23666 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlets/booklets/flyers related to YMCA and Army, 23665 (Box 8)
- Series IV: Visuals, n.d.; 23642 (Box 9, Folder 1-18)
  - Subseries A: Postcards, 23651 (Box 9, Folder 1-11)
    - California, 23662 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Cambridge, Massachusetts, 23661 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - East Northfield, Massachusetts, 23660 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - North Carolina, 23659 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Texas, 23658 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Mount Vernon and Alexandria, Virginia, 23657 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - China, 23656 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Europe, 23655 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Great Britain, 23654 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Japan, 23653 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - US Army and YMCA, World War I, 23652 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Subseries B: Photographs, 23643 (Box 9, Folder 12-18)
    - YMCA and Army, 23650 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - School, 23649 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Places, 23648 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Individuals, 23647 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Groups, 23646 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Individuals and groups, 23645 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Negatives with prints made by AFM [Andrew Forest Muir], 1957; 23644 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Series V: Addenda (Box 10)
  - New Mexico Military Institute Memory Book (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Friends O'Mine Address Book (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook from Student Summer Conference, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1907-01-01-1907-12-25 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Pocket Notes (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Marbled, Caramel-Colored, Pocket Notebook (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Dark Brown Small Pocket Notebook (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Journal (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Rice Institute: Scrapbook of Memories, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mother's Hair (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Grandmother's Hair (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ribbon from S.S. President Roosevelt (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Insignia (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Name Card and Plate (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photos, Clippings, and Postcards (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Photos and Negatives (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Family (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: P. Murdoch (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Sophie Hill (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Friends (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Friends (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Miscellanous (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Series VI: Diplomas (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Satire, 1903-06-25 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of German, 1903-06-30 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Botany, 1903-06-30 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Greek, 1903-06-30 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of History, 1903-06-25 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Mathematics, 1903-06-25 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Philosophy, 1903-06-25 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of English, 1903-06-25 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of French, 1904-06-30 (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma from School of Historical and Political Science, 1904-06-30 (Box 11)
  - Theological Diploma (Box 11)
  - The University of the South Diploma (Box 11)